Today we're happy to have
Nathan Lambert, a research
scientist at the Allen Institute
for AI, who focuses on RLHF
and the author of
interconnects.ai.
He'll be presenting
a really cool talk
on aligning open
language models today.
So thank you for
joining us, Nathan.
Yeah, thanks for the intro.
OK, this is a long time coming.
This is a brief intro
on why I'm doing this.
I think generally,
since ChatGPT,
you'll see a lot has
obviously happened.
But I don't think it's
been a blur for me
as much as anyone else.
So taking the time
to retell what
has happened in this
fine-tuning and alignment space
since ChatGPT
happened is something
that I thought was a
worthy undertaking.
So this is not really
a one-on-one lecture,
but it will probably
give you a lot
of context on why people are
mentioning certain things
and what still matters
and what does not.
So hopefully this is fun.
I can see the chat.
I don't know
exactly if questions
are going to come to me or if
I will see it the whole time.
I think clarifying
questions are good, maybe
not discussions the whole time.
And I'll try to keep
sure that there's
time for questions at the end.
So let's get into it.
Generally, we're going to
talk about language models,
it's what everyone wants
to talk about these days.
I need to do some
of the older history
so that I can talk
about recent history.
The place that I like
to start is actually
with Claude Shannon, who
had this paper talking
about approximating--
arranging characters to
create language models.
That's probably why Anthropic
called their models Claude.
That's pretty well-known.
And a lot has happened since
these very early papers
on predicting sequences of text.
And this is largely built
on this loss function,
which is called the
autoregressive loss function.
So if you have this training
example where you have something
like "I saw a" you're trying to
predict what comes after this,
the whole idea is that there's
going to be one correct token
that is the correct label.
And their training loss
is going to increase
the probability of that token
and decrease the probability
of everything else.
This very simple loss function
classifying which token to use
and actually predict
has enabled wild things.
And this took
another turn in 2017
when this transformer
paper was born.
Attention is all you need.
Everyone here has
heard about this.
It's a great exercise
to actually dig
into what the attention
mechanism is doing.
Not the focus of this talk.
We'll quickly kind
of keep going.
In 2018, there was
three main things.
These are slightly out of order.
ELMo was the earliest
one, which was
contextualized word embeddings.
And the same year, we also
had GPT-1 and BERT released,
which is the beginning of core
ideas on which modern language
models and transformers were
trending towards and just
getting these better
models, training on large--
large internet scaled corpora.
BERT was a classifier.
GPT-1 was generating text.
And we continue along these
trends through the years.
GPT-2 is when we started
learning about scaling laws.
And if you use orders of
magnitude more compute,
the actual test
loss will continue
to decrease in a linear fashion
with respect to the log compute.
These ideas now are
commonplace when
we talk about language models.
GPT-2 also pioneered
a lot of discussions
on releasing language models.
So GPT-2, when it
was first announced,
they were holding access
back because of the risks
of language models.
And this started a lot
of the conversations
around what you
should or should not
release with language models.
They eventually
actually released GPT-2,
and you can download the models
on Hugging Face and use them.
But this is where that kind
of conversation around release
strategies emerged.
In 2020 is when
language models really
started to be noticeably good.
So GPT-3 is when a
lot of people were
like, whoa, this can actually
do really interesting things.
If I create a really
clever prompt,
figure out how to give it
my information correctly,
and GPT-3 could
do a ton of things
with this few-shot or
multi-shot learning, which
is when you give it a few
examples in the prompt
and then ask it to do
another rendition of it.
And with this power
came many harms.
And this is a
discussion of, what
are the risks of
releasing language models?
What types of groups
will be hurt by this?
Very important problems
that culminated in 2021
with the stochastic parrots
paper, which is arguing about
whether or not language models
can be too big, is in the title.
But it's really a critique
on how we should be
thinking about language models.
What are the limits of them?
Are they actually
doing the things?
Like, are they actually
thinking or doing
any of these human things?
Or are they just kind of
following patterns in the data?
And then just the year
after, this is like the--
it's like the tragedy
of syntactic parrots
because no one
talks about it now,
is that ChatGPT
came the year later
and totally reshaped the whole
narrative around language
models one more time.
And this is really
where we start
today's talk, is like, how
does this idea of alignment
emerge in ChatGPT?
And then what
happens after this?
So the question that
I ask myself is like--
or I tell a lot of people is,
can ChatGPT exist without RLHF?
And what we saw in
the release day--
so if you go back and read the
actual OpenAI blog about RLHF,
they list all these limitations.
But they say that RLHF
was an important tool
to launching ChatGPT.
And the limitations
that they list
are really the things that
we're still researching
and that we're talking
about in this talk.
It's a great blog
post to go back to.
But a good way to frame it is
that RLHF seems to be necessary
but is not sufficient.
You can't do something
like ChatGPT or Gemini
or Claude with a
technique that--
without something like RLHF.
But it's not the thing--
like, pretraining is still
most of the work, but the
fact that RLHF is needed
is really important
to contextualize
all these improvements
that we've
seen in the open in the
last 14 months or so.
Some examples that
I like to cite
on RLHF being relied upon-- you
can list many more models here
than I have.
This figure from Anthropic's
"Constitutional AI"
paper is the single one that
I go back to all the time,
showing how just using RLHF
can get these more desirable
behaviors from their model
in really dramatic ways.
So these Elo measurements
aren't calibrated,
so we don't know how to
compare Llama 3 on this chart
compared to Anthropic's models.
But the level of
investment that Anthropic
has had in these
kind of techniques
and showing this kind of
wide-ranging improvements
of their models with
RLHF is a kind flag
that we can follow to try
to learn how to do alignment
with this much precision and
with this much kind of impact
as places like Anthropic
or OpenAI will have.
One such example is
just a simple quote
from the Llama 2 paper, which
is like the colloquial way
of reading this quote,
which I will read,
is that, whoa, RLHF
worked really easily.
And what the quote
is, is "Meanwhile,
reinforcement learning,
known for its instability,
seemed a somewhat shadowy field
for those in the NLP research
community.
However, reinforcement learning
proved highly effective,
particularly given its cost
and time effectiveness."
So this is one of the
biggest endorsements of RLHF.
And it's always fun for me
because I came from the RL side,
and then I've been learning NLP.
But for NLP researchers
to say these things,
like, yes, reinforcement
learning is
known for instability, and
given that it is cost effective
and time effective for an
RL person, that's shocking.
It's like, RL has never
been particularly cost
and time effective.
But for in these language
model domain where we're fine
tuning with it rather than
learning from scratch,
to have people in NLP
that are saying this
is just really striking for
how much impact it can have.
And the timeline of
alignment and open alignment
is really like, when do
we see these benefits?
Like, these benefits
didn't show up in models
that people were playing
with for quite a bit of time.
So this is a little Atlas
that I've thrown together.
I also made a Hugging
Face collection,
where I tried to add all the
models that I talk about to it.
So you can actually
click on the models
or try to use them if you're
so inclined of actually
running the models yourself.
It's just another way of
documenting the artifacts that I
talked about and the
artifacts that-- for me, this
is a good review on,
like, what mattered,
what mattered in this really
noisy journey in the last year.
Of course, some disclaimers--
I'm not covering every
model since ChatGPT.
This little plot of model
icons could probably
look more like an exponential
than this capped bar.
And there's so
much history of NLP
that people are building on
in the alignment space that
is totally swept
under the rug here,
a lot of academic and
infrastructure contributions
that I'm not talking
about, but are
really important to this
proliferation of fine-tuning
models.
So just describing what this
image that I have here is,
is summarized--
some of these are based models.
I'm not going to
focus on base models
as much as fine-tuned models.
The base models are
extremely important.
Like, none of this
happens without Llama.
None of this happens
without Llama 2.
The base model are the
bedrock of this ecosystem.
And then the alignment
models are what people--
the aligned models are a lot of
times what people can play with
and what you can try out,
what you could do yourself
on much less computing
infrastructure and all
these things.
So I'm going to talk more
about the aligned models,
but everything matters.
It's one big ecosystem.
Another thing that's
not fun but I'm
going to do for the sake
of flag posting, no one
really likes listening
to definitions.
Here are some things that
you'll hear thrown around.
This isn't even all of them when
talking about, quote unquote,
"alignment."
I have here, like,
alignment I've
defined as a general
notion of training a model
to mirror a user's desires.
Really, with any loss
function, it's not restricted.
So there's a difference
between instruction fine-tuning
and supervised fine-tuning.
Instruction fine-tuning
is about trying
to get a model that
will respond to queries,
formatted instructions, while
supervised fine-tuning is
more about learning a
specific tasks capabilities.
These get interchanged
all the time.
Like, that's OK.
It's good to know that
they're different.
And then two more ones
that I need to touch on
and we could go on even
longer is reinforcement
learning from human feedback.
There's this
multi-stage process.
It's a specific tool
for aligning ML models
to human data.
It's a class of tools, so it has
some learn a preference model.
And then you extract
information from it.
So there are so many
different ways to do it.
It's really an approach.
And then there's a
term that I'm trying
to grow, which is preference
fine-tuning, which
could encompass RLHF
methods, like PPO.
But there's a question of, how
do we differentiate something
like direct preference
optimization, which
doesn't use an RL
optimizer from all of RLHF?
And I'll come back
to this, but it's
good to have some common
grounds to build on
because I might be going
through some of these things
pretty quickly.
This is a chapter that
I cover in one slide
because it's really
tapping into a lot
of different personal stories.
It's hard to retell
how crazy things were
when ChatGPT dropped.
People were not really
losing their mind,
but there was a
lot of uncertainty
on what the future held,
especially that it was clear
that language models
were important.
But it is not clear--
there's a lot of
articles on like--
titled, we're going
to reproduce open
ChatGPT, which you can't really
have an open model that does
what a closed product does.
There's a difference between
model weights and this product
that ChatGPT represents, but
there's so much excitement
that everyone is saying they're
going to do these things
and trying to figure out the
right coalitions for actually
doing so.
And it's interesting.
This delay is this
land grab, where people
are learning the basic things.
Like, what is red-teaming?
What is the difference
between a dialogue
agent and a predictive
language model?
What tools should we use?
And everything follows from here
with what people are building.
But like, personally, I just
remember multiple meetings
where people were like,
yeah, you should do it.
You should go try to
build open ChatGPT.
And when you look
back, that goal is just
so wild that so many
people are just going like,
we need to build this
thing in the open source.
And it's just like,
it doesn't even
make sense because
you can't open source
a whole system that way.
But there are some
things that make a bit--
like, this makes
a lot more sense,
which is when things start to
get grounded in actual models.
So the first Llama suite
was released in, I think,
in February.
I have the date in
some notes somewhere.
And then these instruction
tuned models started to show up
on this first Llama model.
The first one to really
crack the narrative
was this Alpaca
model, and it did
a bunch of things that
still are used today.
So this was trained on 52,000
self-constructed style data
distilled from text-davinci-003.
There's a lot in the sentence.
I'll say what
self-construct means.
But this wasn't even data
generated from ChatGPT.
It was generated from one
of OpenAI's API models.
So if we talk about--
this is all on how to apply
instruction fine-tuning.
And this thing I mentioned
on the definition slide.
But really, it's about making
a model that will respond
to specific styles of inputs.
What often happens at
a technical level here
is that the model is learning
to integrate something
called a chat
template, the ability
to include system prompts.
So you want to tell--
you want the model
to know it is an agent.
You want the model to
know what day it is.
Excuse me.
You can do this in the system
prompt, which is something
that the user doesn't see.
But it steers the
behavior of the model.
And instruction
tuning is really where
we make the model capable
of having these behaviors.
But the question is
like, what data are
we training this behavior on?
So the most common example
is you continue training
with this autoregressive
loss function
on question-answer pairs.
So it's like, what
is a transformer?
And then the language model
will predict an answer.
Could be from stack overflow.
It could be something else.
And this example is human data.
But what made Alpaca and a
lot of these early models,
and even today, really
popular and accessible
is by using data
to answer questions
that is generated by an AI.
So this is where the idea of
self-instruct data comes in.
Self-instruct was a paper
from Allen AI and UDub in 2022
before ChatGPT, where
essentially the idea
is, how do we expand on the
distribution and instruction
data that we have, this training
data for fine-tuning a language
model without getting
more humans in the loop?
So what you really
have to do is you
start with some high-quality,
often human prompts.
And then what we now see as
more common practice today
but was very new then is asking
a stronger language model.
Create a list of prompts
that are similar to this
but still diverse.
And then once you have
a list of prompts,
you can use ChatGPT
or another model
to actually generate
completions.
Because then what you
have is a really big list
of question-answer
pairs, but you
don't need to go through the
bottleneck of getting humans
to sit down and
write all of them.
So what Alpaca was really--
why Alpaca worked is because
of realizing this and taking
in this better
model from OpenAI.
So you can see this
figure here on the right
is from the Alpaca paper or
blog post, one of the two.
They took this model from
OpenAI and they asked
it to generate more tasks.
So they had 175 to start, and
then they ended up with over
50,000 tasks.
And they also
generated completions
from this OpenAI model.
And then what they did is they
took these Meta weights that
had just come out, and they
instruction fine-tuning them.
And then you end up with Alpaca.
This is a pattern.
This is a pattern that
we've seen many times
with Alpaca, which is
essentially, you take--
you generate some data from
a stronger language model,
and you fine-tuning on it.
It sounds so obvious today,
but this was the first model
to actually release this.
I can now see
questions coming in.
I'll answer the ones that are
clarifying and stuff like this,
so Thanks for asking them.
And we can come back
to more at the end.
Once Alpaca happened,
it felt like there
was a new model every week.
The second model was Vicuna.
And really, what
they changed was
they added new sources of
prompts to the distribution.
So you can see that
I say ShareGPT.
They also introduced the
idea of LLM-as-a-judge,
which is now obvious from a lot
of their later evaluation work.
But let's talk about why
ShareGPT was so interesting.
So ShareGPT was one
of the only data
sets that got open
language model builders, so
people like me, prompts that
were similar to what people
were asking ChatGPT.
So what was happening was you
would install this browser
plug-in, and it would let you
share your prompts from ChatGPT
on Twitter or whatever.
So it was making it easier
to share the prompts before--
in your conversations, before
OpenAI made a tool to do this.
And now there's
this legal gray area
over the data set because
most of these data sets
are unlicensed, and they
were created without consent.
Or they were released
without consent.
So there's a legal question of
whether or not people should
be trading on this data.
But the fact of the
matter is that ShareGPT
was really important to this
acceleration in progress
on fine-tuning models
because the diversity of data
is just so much
stronger than what
people were going to get from
this Alpaca self-instruct idea.
And it set the bar much higher.
It's only today in the last
few months or six months
for some of them that were
getting data sets that
can replace these.
So you see I mentioned
LMSYS-Chat-1M,
which is just a million
conversations from ChatBotArena,
which took a lot of work to
clean out personal information;
and then a project from
the Allen Institute
of AI, which is WildChat, which
is really similar to ShareGPT.
But the users were giving
consent at the start
that their data was going
to be collected and released
in exchange for using a
language model for free.
So there's a lot of
happenstance in the story where
something like this,
which is legally gray--
and the data is still on Hugging
face, but it looks kind of odd--
where these little things helped
enable the ecosystem, even
though, looking
back, it's like, oh,
we don't know if that
should have happened.
Following Vicuna is one called
Koala, also from Berkeley.
And look at the timeframes.
It's pretty obvious
that a lot of these
were developed
concurrently, and then
their release dates just happen
to be slightly different.
Koala is mostly known for having
a different diverse set of data
sets.
They use some from Alpaca.
They use some from
ShareGPT again.
They also use Anthropic
data that has been released,
and they had some human
evaluation from grad students.
So this just added
more data diversity,
and the evaluations
weren't necessarily better.
But it was an important
model that a lot of people
noticed just from bringing
back up these new data
sets that had been in the
literature from years prior.
Something that you might
ask looking at these slides
is that it's like, why
weight differences?
I have all these slides,
like, weight diff to LLaMA 7B,
weight diff.
Essentially, when
Llama was released,
it was released
as research only.
And you had to-- and it was
distributed to researchers
upon request, and the
license prohibited people
from updating Llama
1 to Hugging Face.
So it's this
annoying phase where,
in order to use a
model on Hugging Face,
you had to clone it.
And then you had to run a script
to convert it with this delta
into the new model in
order to actually use it.
So this is a really frustrating
phase from a user perspective
because it just made
experimentation have one more
barrier to entry.
And thankfully, it was
changed with Llama 2,
but it was really
something that many people
dealt with at the time.
And we now today see
different license restrictions
on how Llama is used.
I mean, the Llama
3 released today--
essentially, if I fine-tuning
a model for my research
and I release it, too, Llama
3 needs to be in the name.
So if I want to release
a new Tulu model,
it would have to be
Llama 3, Tulu 4 DPO.
It's like, the namings
are going to be crazy.
But there's always
been restrictions
on using Llama weights
or how you share them.
And the final model that
I group into this batch
of this real first
swing was Dolly.
So Dolly was fine-tuning
from a different base model.
It was fine-tuning
from the Pythia models
from a Luther, which were
a suite of early scaling
experiments from EleutherAI,
which is still used extensively.
But they added some
human-written data
to the loop, which is really
important because almost all
of the projects
that I'll mention
today talk about synthetic data
or data derived from OpenAI.
There's only a few of them that
actually added new human data
to the loop, and this is what
everyone remembered Dolly for.
And a lot of its
performance limitations
were probably from
the base model Pythia,
which is trained in a time
where this type of inference
that people expect
wasn't as popular.
And it was before--
the scaling laws were
thought of differently.
You can see through
these where we're
going to start with different
model sizes and different MT
bench scores.
I'll talk about what MT
bench is in a few slides.
It's an evaluation tool.
And this is really just to
ground you on what the--
how the scores would
change over time.
So I have these
throughout the talk
as we go through
different models
just to show how the scores
continue to progress over time
from one small change to another
as the community gets better
at these things.
While I was talking
about human data,
so remember, Dolly is
all about human data.
Probably still the single
busiest human coordination
project for data generation
was OpenAssistant.
I think it's easy now if
you get into fine-tuning
to see the open system
data set and not
realize how important it was
to the process of alignment
in this whole summer.
And it is still used today.
So essentially, there's
this quote on the top.
But the leaders ran
a community project
to generate
human-written prompts
and these
human-written responses
in many different
languages with rating them.
So you could use it
as preferences with--
the slide has a bug,
where it's like,
it has over 10,000
annotated trees and over
1,000 volunteers.
This is still used
extensively today,
will come up again in the talk.
They also released models.
So the first one of the first
model used on Hugging Chat,
which I don't remember
the launch date of,
was an OpenAssistant model.
So OpenAssistant was probably
the first majorly successful
project of the era, and the
data set is still used today.
Where I will end
this talk is saying
that we need more
things like this,
is really one of the
most important things,
is we need more human
data in the open.
And this is a quick aside.
It's kind of out of
the flow of the talk.
But on April 28 of 2023--
typo on the slide-- of April
28 of 2023, stable Vicuna
was released from
CarperAI, which looks now
like the style of
training models,
except for the data set,
which is now popular.
They got PPO to work.
They had some human
evaluations that were solid.
It was a good chat model.
It wasn't out of distribution,
but CarperAI was really
ahead at the time.
And then it seems like
priorities kind of shifted
from stability.
But it's important to know the
extent by which there were still
some players who knew how to
do RLHF really early on, even
though there were pretty rare.
This is the last--
this is the last
slide of this kind
of first chapter on
instruction tuning,
was the idea of
QLoRA, which unlocked
a whole new bunch of
players into actually
being able to fine-tune models.
So for the quick
60-second overview,
LoRA stands for Low
Rank Adaptation,
which is the idea of
can freeze some model--
you freeze most of
the model weights,
and you add new weights to
specific layers that you can
then fine-tuning as if you were
fine-tuning the whole model.
You use the same approach
of instruction data
with question answering, but
it takes much less memory.
QLoRA was a technique
that built upon this
by adding very specific
quantization and GPU
tricks to make it
so that it memory
requirements to fine-tune
models was even lower.
Tim Dettmers and team also
released this Guanaco model
with it, which was another
big step up in performance
of these models.
I have a few more slides
on it, on the methods.
So you can see on the right this
difference, full fine-tuning
and LoRA.
They look similar, where LoRA
you have fewer parameters,
as what the smaller shapes mean.
And QLoRA, they
quantize the base model
that you're propagating
gradients through
to save most of the memory.
So this is an
approximation of, if you're
fine-tuning different model
sizes on the top, so 7 billion,
13 billion, 30 billion,
with full fine-tuning
different amount of bits
but full fine-tuning
versus LoRa versus QLoRA.
And you can see,
for reference, one
A100 GPU has about 80
gigabytes of memory.
And these are really
hard GPUs to get.
Plenty of consumer
GPUs will only
have 24 to 32
gigabytes of memory.
So you need to use these QLoRA
techniques to actually get
the ability to fine-tune models
at the 7 or 13 billion parameter
size.
And like, Guanaco
did this, and they
released 33 billion and
65 billion parameter Llama
fine-tunes, which
were clear steps up
in the kind of state
of the art at the time.
And they also figured out ways
to filter this OpenAssistant
data set that I
mentioned, and this kind
of filtered version
of OpenAssistant
is what is still
most popular today.
I'm going to pause and
skim through the questions
and see if there's
anything on that section.
And if not, I'll save the
relevant ones for later.
OK, I'm going to keep going.
They're great questions,
and I appreciate them.
But they're mostly
not specific enough
where it's worth the digression.
This chapter 2 phase
is really where
it seemed like things were a
little bit slower on the ground.
But when we look back at
a lot of the things that
came out of this time, like
the DPO paper was in this era.
Everyone read it, but we didn't
know what to do with it yet.
And the new evaluations
are still really used.
Transitioning in,
setting the scene
for being not sure if
things work, a lot of people
are continuing to try to build
on these LoRA methods and QLoRA
methods.
I remember a lot of
excitement at Hugging Face,
where we were setting
up our RLHF pipeline,
where we could do RLHF on
7 billion parameter models.
And we could maybe do
it on a consumer GPU.
It was really cool to
see the loss going down.
It's great to bring more
people into the space.
But weeks and weeks would go by.
And they're like, why
has no one picked up
what we released
in the blog post
and trained a really
good model with it?
And the kind of consensus now
is that these LoRA methods just
have some sort of weird
limitation in how you use them
or how the gradients flow
that make it much, much harder
to get a really good model out.
If you only have a
certain number of GPUs,
such that LoRA is your only
option, definitely use it.
But for people that have more
GPUs, figuring out how to scale
is normally a better
solution than just
using something like
LoRA that fits in
is easier in the short term.
Another defining moment of this
era was the Llama 2 backlash.
I'm guessing some
people remember
this, which is like, the famous
line was people ask Llama
how to kill a Python process.
And it would say, no.
And this really started a
whole bunch of new discussions
around what kind
of alignment means
or what model should
or should not do.
Here's an example from a
paper for a safety evaluation
test set called XSTest,
and it's just like,
should chat models be safe?
Or should they follow the
instructions that I want?
And this is a
fundamental question.
It'll differ by
organization, and it
will differ by individual.
And this is the point where
this became very serious
and something that
people actually
had to reckon with because there
were models that were actively--
people were really disagreeing
with the specific take.
I don't have any
clear solution to it.
But one of the
things that led to
is this idea of
uncensored models.
It's a really popular
category on Hugging Face
right now, where the idea is you
remove filtering-- so if we're
using synthetic data
and ask a language model
a question-- like, if I ask
ChatGPT how to make a bomb,
it's going to say, I'm sorry.
I'm a language model.
I shouldn't make this.
And the idea of
uncensored models
is to remove those
points from our--
remove those points from
our fine-tuning data set.
I think there's a lot of
confusion over the name
because language
models were never--
at this stage, really aren't
censored to begin with.
But it's really
that the data set
and the method for
creating these data
sets needed more
filtering, or they needed
some way of becoming unbiased.
So there's a lot
of people now that
only build models to try
to make them unbiased
against any sort of refusal.
A refusal is when you ask
a language model something,
and it says, no.
And this goes on today, and this
came out of this Llama 2 thing.
But otherwise, this
is a transition period
where there is a lot of good,
solid models being trained.
But either they didn't have
a lot of documentation.
They didn't have the
right release team
to splash as big as
they should have.
The methods were
complicated to implement
or something like this.
So I could run through
these, and I remember
all these models coming out.
But none of them were really
things that are household names
like Alpaca is today.
Like, the team from
behind WizardLM
where they created this method
called EvolInstruct, which
is a synthetic data method--
like, all these
things were clearly
working for them based on the
models they were generating.
But for whatever
reason, the narrative
wasn't actually changed.
There's some new data
sets from ultra--
like, UltraLM is from an
open BNB in China that
is releasing new data sets, more
people training on ShareGPT.
The model called XwinLM
was the first one
to be a similar
ballpark, and it's also
trained with RLHF, so not
just that carbon model.
But for whatever reason, it's
like these didn't really splash.
And that was this
summer after Llama 2,
where fine-tuning
was chugging along.
But the narrative wasn't
changing all that much,
at least from my perspective.
But that's why I'm here.
But what was happening
in the background
while the models weren't
seeming that different
is that new evaluation tools
were coming out that ended up
being the standard of today.
So you can see the dates here.
So May 3, ChatBotArena, June 8,
AlpacaEval; June 22, MT Bench.
Sometime in early July,
the Open LLM Leaderboard.
All of these things were created
about the same time, where there
was a desperate need to
get some sort of signal
on what our fine-tuned
models are doing in the open.
We don't have the
capability of paying humans
to compare our
responses, like they
do at anthropic,
where they're always
trying new models on humans.
That's way too expensive.
We need something that you
could sit down as an engineer
and get feedback in
10 to 15 minutes.
So I run through these in order.
And a lot of these
are obvious, but it's
important to take this
from the perspective of,
what can I use when I'm
trying to align models?
And what is an
immediate feedback
versus what is this
long-term signal?
So ChatBotArena is
obviously fantastic.
Like, everyone looks at
this today as something
that is defining--
it's like defining
corporate strategy.
It's defining the biggest
language model players,
like if Claude 3 is
better than GPT-4.
But if I'm an engineer, A,
many small [INAUDIBLE] riders
aren't going to get
their models in.
And B, it takes--
especially previously,
it used to take weeks
to get your model's rating.
But now it takes days.
Like, I need to know what
my models are before I
decide to actually release it.
So that's the
biggest thing, where
I know I need something
beyond ChatBotArena, just
for my engineering development.
And this is where
I like AlpacaEval
and MT Bench really thrive.
So AlpacaEval got-- slide
format and got changed,
but I'll just keep
rolling through this.
AlpacaEval is the idea, if
you have a list of promts,
that you compare to a
strong other base model,
like OpenAI's
Davinci-003 or GPT-4.
And then you ask a language
model which is better.
And the data set
here is compiled
from all these popular data sets
that I have been talking about
so far, so data sets from
Open Assistant, Vicuna, Koala,
Anthropic.
All these data sets that
people have been using--
they took the test
sets from those.
And that's what
AlpacaEval mirrors.
It's a known thing.
It has some limitations because
there's only so many prompts.
And it's like asking a language
model to provide a rating,
is going to have
some ceiling where
we don't know how to compare
two really good models.
So it has more samples than
MT Bench, so there's more--
so there's just
smaller error bars,
and it's easier to use because
it's a single-turn generation.
But we've heard about the length
bias for a really long time,
and it's not clear how to
interpret these top results.
So this is an older
screenshot of the leaderboard.
But what is beating a
model 95% of the time
mean to another language model?
That's the questions
that we can't really
answer in the short term.
AlpacaEval 2 came out, which
takes steps to this, where it--
rate compares to GPT-4
rather than Davinci-003.
Davinci-003 was an
InstructGPT variant.
But at the end of
the day, GPT-4 is
answering these questions in
the Alpaca style really well.
So what does beating
GPT-4 exactly mean?
And I think we need to get more
specific in our evaluations
because I don't really know if I
care too much about a 20% or 30%
score on AlpacaEval 2 because
I don't know what it means.
And this is one this
is the opaqueness
of all of our evaluations.
We'll see this time
and time again,
where we don't know what
an increase in score means.
That's like the next step after
being able to do it easily.
This update was pretty recent.
MT Bench is pretty
similar, where,
instead of comparing
to one model,
you ask a language
model to provide
a score to a list of prompts.
So if I have a
model I'm training,
I generate the completion
to 80 diverse prompts.
And then I ask GPT-4,
hey, from 0 to 10,
how good were each
of those completions?
And this is good, but it
runs into the same problem
of like, what if our model
is getting really good?
If our model is getting
really good, it's just like--
it becomes saturated.
GPT-4 only gets to
about 9, and there's
only about 80 prompts
in the evaluation set
and all of these things.
And one of the nuanced points
is that there's actually
a variance.
So even if you set
the temperature to 0,
GPT-4 versions change.
Your own generations from your
model you're trying to train
can change.
And this makes it better,
where it's like, OK,
I can tell if a
model was really bad,
if MT Bench and AlpacaEval
have really low scores.
But it's hard to--
still, we have this goal
for a precise evaluation.
So in pretraining, we have
MT Bench and HellaSwag
and all-- or sorry.
In pretraining, we have MMLU and
HellaSwag and all these things
that people can look at
and average over 10 tasks.
And if you get a 2% improvement
on average, you're doing great.
But we don't have
this clear indicator
in alignment evaluation.
The Open LLM Leaderboard
was the same, where it's--
this came out of the team I
was working on at Hugging Face,
where we were just trying
to evaluate more models
to get more signal,
which was that we needed
to know what our
competitors are doing
and get some ballpark estimate.
And what this grew
into is this whole kind
of ecosystem supporting
discovery tool
just because getting
any signal is so useful.
So this is where we're
starting with evaluation,
which was just no signal.
And why this leaderboard
was so successful
is because it gave
everyone access
to a little bit more
signal on the models
that they're evaluation.
But it didn't really solve any
of the fundamental problems,
and it didn't show us that,
like, doing offline models
would actually make
the scores go up.
It's starting to
get better today,
but that's a year on from the
launch of this leaderboard.
So this is like, these
problems are still--
this is talking about a
section from July of 2023.
And it seems like
the things that if I
were to go into-- go into work
and talk to people, what we're
going to do with our
new models, like,
these are the same questions
that we're still asking,
which is why these evaluation
schools are still so useful.
And it's why people still
talk about AlpacaEval.
But it shows how much of an
opportunity there still is.
So this is a summary of
what I was talking about.
It's like, how easy is it
to use these evaluations?
ChatBotArena is everything.
Andre Karpathy tweets
about it, and it's great.
And you can go there,
and you can use models.
But like, I don't know
how to make sense of that,
as if I'm trying to sit down
every day and write code.
And the AlpacaEval
and MT Bench mostly
solve this by being cheap
and pretty accessible.
But I really, really think
there's a huge opportunity here
to come out with more.
So like, a colleague at AI2
launched WildBench, which
is a good tool that fits in.
It's like a ChatBotArena
AlpacaEval hybrid,
and you can use it
a little bit faster.
It's like, how are we going to
continue to push this along?
is a great question, and I would
love to hear what people think.
And take another pause.
I think we're getting
good questions in the chat
around RLHF and other things.
To what extent are-- do
aligned models actually
reason about whether
user intent is malicious
rather than perform target
detection to detect--
to avoid unsafe topics?
This is a question
that I wanted to read
because it gets at this
model versus system topic.
So when ChatGPT was
released on day one,
it has an output filter
that does moderation.
The language model that is
instruction [INAUDIBLE] RLHF
[? too ?] and generates
a bunch of text, and then
a separate model says yes or no.
And that's where it
actually does detection.
And with the release
of Llama 3, there's
another model that's
called Llama Guard.
And this is a classifier
which will take this text,
do the moderation, and say which
type of unsafe topic it is.
The actual model
that is generating
does no reasoning over what
is actually an unsafe topic.
So I'll come back
to the other ones.
I'm going to do some discussions
about RLHF right now.
So this will give good grounds
for where we can continue
some of these discussions on.
There's ORPO or Reinforce.
I don't cover all of
them in the lecture,
but I lead on to why we
would talk about them.
So this chapter is when I
started to get validation
as an RL researcher that
being opportunistic and going
to work in language models
was actually a good idea.
For a lot of this, there
was a lot of uncertainty
over if the people--
if people in this open ecosystem
were even going to be able
to use RLHF at all, or if
being a, quote unquote,
"RLHF researcher" for me meant
I was going to do instruction,
fine-tuning, and talk about
[INAUDIBLE] and never think
about RL again.
It turned out to be wrong.
I'm going to review
some fundamentals, just
to make sure we're
talking the same language
as we talk about this.
And this will lead into direct
preference optimization.
So there's a reason
why I'm doing math.
I know this is not
a normal lecture,
but here's the equation where--
you'll see this in RLHF papers.
This is what we're optimizing
when we're optimizing RLHF.
It looks nebulous here.
I'll break it down.
So on the left side, we're
really maximizing with respect
to some policy pi.
This reward that is
parametrized by a network phi,
and we're have a
penalty that is this KL
term, which is the distance from
our policy to some reference.
We want to increase reward, but
we want to constrain the model
so that it doesn't-- this kind
of optimization doesn't go too
far.
And the primary
questions when doing this
is, how do we implement
a good reward function?
And how do we
optimize the reward?
This is a really
RL-centric way of doing it,
which is like, if you give me a
reward function, I can optimize.
And the classic RL idea
was, I'm in an environment.
That environment has the
reward function built in.
In RLHF, we're designing
our own reward function.
So this adds a lot of weirdness
to the actual optimization
that we're doing.
And what we do is--
to get this reward
function is we
learn what is called a
preference or a reward model.
And the most popular
way to do this
is to take a
language model that's
predicting the separation
of two preferences.
This is called a
Bradley-Terry model, which
goes back to some economics.
But the key idea
is that the reward
will be proportional
to the probability
that the text they
have would be chosen
over any other arbitrary text.
[? Quickly ?] sounds
really theory like,
but it outputs a scalar, which
is now a reward function.
And it's based on
this pairwise data.
So the idea is,
with this equation,
what if we just use gradient
ascent on this equation?
And instead of trying to
learn a preference model
and learn this R,
what if we just
use gradient ascent directly?
This is really what direct
preference optimization
is doing.
There's a bunch of math in
here to get what this R is.
But this was
released back in May,
so we've already
moved on months ahead.
This chapter starts in
late September, October.
Back in May, when we're still
talking about OpenAssistant,
this DPO paper came out.
It's a fantastic paper.
If you haven't read
it, it's a great way
to learn about
language model math.
It's worth reading.
But the core idea is like, why
are we spending all this time
learning a reward model when
we can just use gradient ascent
and solve for the loss function?
Some key ideas to
think about with DPO
is that DPO is extremely
simple to implement.
On the right here side
is the example code
from the DPO paper, where it's
like, as long as you have access
to the log probs
from a model, which
is a very core thing for
training language models,
you can compute the DPO loss.
Because of this, because
the loss function
is at a nice abstraction,
it scales nicely
with existing libraries.
And what it's actually doing
is training an implicit reward
function.
So the reward is a
function of the log probs.
I don't have the equation
here, because it quickly
becomes a rabbit hole.
But whatever the whole DPO
versus PPO debate means or--
or RPO, I don't even remember
what the paper, it's title
is, we're going to see
a lot of these things
because it's simple,
and it scales well.
That doesn't necessarily mean
the fundamental limits are
higher, but sometimes
it doesn't matter
if the limits are higher if
it's easier to make progress
on something because
it feels better
when progress is being made.
So that's really
a core thing, is
we'll keep seeing these models.
And we are.
And there's this
whole debate that
has gone on crushing a whole
bunch of these questions
by redirecting them in
a very political manner.
But it's like, should
we use REINFORCE?
What about other things?
They're very different
styles of optimization.
So in one half, we're
using RL update rules,
which is ultimately about
learning a value function
and then learning to update--
taking gradient steps with
respect to that value function.
In DPO we're taking
gradient steps directly
from the probabilities
of the language model.
They're very different
optimization regimes.
And there's this
great meme where all--
there was a month where the
whole NLP Twitter was just
arguing about this.
But both of them are continuing
to progress, and that is good.
Like, it will not just
be one or the other.
So what really made this
debate kick into gear
was this release of the Zephyr
beta model from Hugging Face.
It's after I left Hugging
Face for the team was on,
and it was the first model
to make a splash with DPO.
And it was a big step up in
how models were perceived.
This model was added to
the You search engine.
People are using all
sorts of crazy things,
so it just felt
really good to use.
It was building on
this better base model.
Mistral had come out.
And new data set, this
UltraFeedback data
set that I mentioned
is still one
of the core data sets used today
when we're practicing alignment.
This was back in
September or October
that this model came back.
One of the core things to
getting DPO to work was using
really low learning
rates, like 5E minus 7.
There's memes about 3E minus 4
being the only learning rate you
need to do deep learning
and changing it being kind
of a joke.
DP0 is the case where that
is not even remotely true.
And then you can see the
MT Bench scores, again,
continuing to rise.
So this is a validation
proof that DPO works.
That came four months after
the paper was released.
That delay is something
that nobody expected.
We were losing hope
on DPO at many times,
and now look at where it is.
And then when I joined
AI2, they were already
working on this project.
And I just helped kind of
get it across the line.
It's like the classic advisor
thing, where sometimes it's
just easier.
And it is the first model to
scale to 70 billion parameters.
The last question was, oh,
yeah, DPO works on small models.
Will anyone ever use
it on a big model?
And answer is, yes.
And it's built on
the same recipe
as Zephyr with a little bit
different instruction tuning
data sets.
But scores continue to climb.
This model was so close to
beating GPT-3.5 on Chatbot
Arena.
It was like a couple
Elo points below.
So we didn't get the title of
being the first one to do that.
But open models were starting to
get that kind of chatty behavior
that for so long had eluded them
because we hadn't figured out
scale, because we hadn't
figured out these data sets.
So it was great progress, very
important, and major transition
in my career, where
now it's like, OK,
our RLHF methods
really can work.
And these weren't just--
I was not the only one
touching things that did this.
A couple other projects that
are really important-- so NVIDIA
had SteerLM, where SteerLM was
collecting feedback data where
there was attributes on it, like
how helpful the message was,
how concise the message was.
And they did a
bunch of fine-tuning
and released good,
very solid models.
And they also showed
that PPO is better
than DPO, which is interesting.
And then Berkeley came out
with this Starling-LM-alpha,
where they had a new
preference data set, Nectar,
which is still looked at today.
And then they also use
this kind of PPO method
after training a reward model.
And both of these came
out about the same time.
And they're like, huh, DPO
isn't doing as well for us.
The models are really good.
Recently, the second
Starling model came out.
Its reward model is very
strong in my testing.
It's a 7B model that's almost
reaching ChatGPT levels
and Chatbot Arena.
It's crazy how fast
these models are going,
but we still get a
lot of models that
are built with PPO or with DPO.
It's really not one or
the other at this point.
OK I think this is a
reasonable time for me to take
a couple of these questions.
I might come back to
them in more slides.
But someone asks, is there a
particular alignment method
that I use?
This is teasing a paper, but
there was a recent paper that
came out where--
I don't remember the group.
I can find it later.
But they did what they call a
systematic study of PPO and DPO,
and they showed
that PPO is better.
I will say that in the
experiments that I'm seeing,
AllenAI.
I'm also seeing
PPO to be stronger.
And we hope to release
this stuff soon.
It's not a one
crushes the other.
It's that we're seeing that
there's-- for some reason,
PPO is just getting a
bit more performance.
And then the logical question
is, why not reinforce?
which is another one
of these questions.
I would love to try it.
It's just like, we have
the code that we have.
And we don't want to touch
things that are working well.
And there's just
so few people that
are working in this
space, which are--
I'm like, let's get more
people working on these things
because there's
so few people that
can answer all these questions.
So there's another
question that says,
like, some say REINFORCE can
work as well as, if not better,
than PPO.
It probably can.
It comes down to
your infrastructure,
carefully fine-tuning it,
what people are excited about,
and a lot of luck.
So we'll see these continue to
play out throughout the year,
but it's complicated.
I'll come back to
the Llama 3 question.
I have one slide for
that in a little bit.
But really this
modern ecosystem is
how investment in releasing
open models that people can use
is continuing to grow into 2024.
I think there's always been
this tenuous period of like,
there's only a few people
releasing these aligned models.
There's these important
people in the ecosystem that
are just doing this because
they want to, and it's for fun.
They might have a day job.
And it's like, how
long can this go on?
Like, what are the
limitations on this?
But in 2024, we've really
seen more companies
come into the space.
And someone drew Meta
Llama 3 on the screen.
I was like, I was talking
to [? co-workers. ?]
And they're like, yeah, you're
going to need to keep adding
models.
You're never going to be
able to give this lecture.
Yeah, it's a losing battle.
I know.
But the modern-- there's just
way more types of models.
So I get away with
not having Llama 3
on this specific slide because
I'm talking about diversity
of players and models, not
just the fact that there
are more great models.
So there's interesting models,
like this one, Genstruct
from NousResearch in
the last few months,
where it's a specifically fine
tuned model for rephrasing
any text into instructions.
So if you have a
book and you want
to model to be able to
answer questions about this,
why don't we just throw it
at this rephrasing question--
this rephrasing model?
And the teams that
I work on, AI2,
were trying to release
instruction models where
every single thing that we've
done to train it is documented
and reproducible, from data
to what compute it was.
There's just, these models are
getting new features in these
little ways other than just
being the, quote unquote,
"best open model," such as these
corporate entities that are
going for really
standing out in the open.
So there's Databricks
DBRX model,
Cohere's command R+ model.
I think people are mostly
blindsided by Cohere releasing
model weights, but it
was the first open model
to pass GPT-4 on Chatbot Arena.
And that has been
a long time coming.
I think beating GPT-4 on a
human evaluation is not easy.
And yes, the open is still a
year behind, but that's fine.
As long as we have a
functioning ecosystem,
it will continue to grow.
Then there's other things, like,
interesting research models.
Like, Rho came out, which
does data weighting.
We're finally starting to get
multilingual models with Aya,
which is also from Cohere.
People are getting more
mixture of expert models
to train on, which
is just a bit more
of an efficient
pretraining equation.
State-space models
are really taking off.
They had this moment
in December with Mamba
and now it's continuing in 2024.
So there's just a lot going on.
And this makes me feel
good because it's like, OK,
I just have to keep doing what
I'm doing and encouraging people
to participate.
And we're going to keep
being able to do this fun
thing of figuring out how to
make models and share them
with people.
This is my slide for Llama 3.
The reason why I didn't make a
lot of slides about this all day
is that Llama 3's
release is more
about scaling of the
ecosystem as a whole
than it is about alignment.
The Llama 2 paper was extremely
detailed about alignment.
And we're going to get
a Llama 3 paper soon,
if you can believe
multiple sources at Meta,
which I choose to.
And when the Llama
3 paper comes out
is when we will learn all
the interesting alignment
things that they have done.
That being said, they're
very unlikely to release
the human preference
data that they did.
I'm yet to succeed
in getting them
to release a reward
model for Llama 2
or Llama 3 from alignment.
So we have more work to do
on getting Meta to support
this kind of open alignment
ecosystem to the same extent
that they are supporting
the pretrainging ecosystem.
And this kind of scaling story
that I'm saying very much
connects to the previous slide,
where scaling and solving this
is very much determined by the
markets and capital incentives.
But so long as
scaling is continuing
to happen in the open
ecosystem, it just
means that more players
are going to stick around.
And in some ways, it
feeds back into itself,
where if this Llama 3
is rumored to have--
or they're training
a $400 billion
parameter model, which we're not
100% sure that the weights will
be released.
But it seems like that's
Mark Zuckerberg's intent.
And having that, which
is about GPT-4 quality,
really changes what you can do
to get language models running
in your products.
So Llama 3 and how many people
are playing in the open space
right now goes to
show that we have
more of the same coming, which
is interesting models coming
on a weekly basis.
And most people are just kind
of accommodated to it now.
Like, people don't freak
out when there's a new--
well, they like Mistral's model
because there's a magnet link,
and it's funny.
But we're used to
it, and I still
expect that to be the case
for the next year or two,
with this pace just
being how it is.
And it's really fun to follow.
And I just think
that it's not a time
to be worried about
scooping, being scooped,
but to just keep figuring
out where you can contribute,
whether it's on
evaluation or some
of these other alignment methods
that people have talked about.
So I have a quick thing on
current directions, which
is-- we'll come back to
some of these data things
that I mentioned multiple
times, and then we
can get to questions.
And the thing that
people want to know a lot
is, are open models going to
catch up to closed models?
My answer is, probably
not ever completely.
There will be some friction
in the system by a time delay
by which open models are closed.
And open model weights
are not inherently unsafe.
The open versus closed
debate has mostly
converged around this.
But given the
territory that we're
going with in AI,
where we're uncovering
new capabilities
we've never seen,
I think it's OK that
if there's a few months
wait before you have
open weights so you
can run on your laptop, as we're
discovering what AI can do.
If you look at someone if you
look at Maxime's plot with trend
lines showing them, it
shows that open models
are getting closer.
But we're not really sure if
open models will stay closer
on Chatbot Arena
in the long term.
There will always be an
open and closed category
because there is demand to
have models that are tuned
to what you want them to do.
So this leans into my
current directions.
Data is the biggest
limitation to alignment,
which is we have
two or three data
sets that are driving all the
research and open alignment.
Anthropic HH data set
for my friend Deep, got
that uploaded back
in 2022, I think,
UltraFeedback from OpenBMB.
And Nectar from
berkeley-nest/Nexusflow with
the Starling models are what
most people are focusing on.
We need more, particularly
if humans wrote it,
to add more diversity to our
models and more robustness.
DPO is continuing in
an academic sense.
There is a comedy of
papers extending DPO.
So this is odds ratio
preference optimization, which
doesn't need a reference model,
constrained DPO, identity
preference optimization.
I don't remember what BCO is,
and then I can't pronounce
the KTO authors but like
[? Kavertsky-something ?]
optimization from Contextual
and Stanford DNO, sDPO,
which is like sequential
DPO, and Self-Reward.
There are so many,
and that's good.
And that trend will continue.
And at the same time, we're
seeing more model sizes.
Most alignment happened
at the 7 or 13B scale.
I think there's a large drive
to make smaller models aligned.
Google is releasing 1
billion parameter models,
but it's also an
opportunity where
there aren't that many
people playing in the space.
But it's something that
a lot of people want.
Just because they run
these models locally,
making them smaller
makes it way easier.
And then running back to two
themes throughout this lecture
is, what are
specific evaluations
that we should be building?
And how do we
personalize these models?
They go hand in hand.
These are the things
that I'm thinking about.
I welcome feedback from them.
I identified some
people that I'm
following to see where
new models come out.
So I try to release models
AI2, Hugging Face quickly
turns around new aligned
models under the Zephyr brand,
these kind of Berkeley-Nest
and Nexusflow slow people
building data sets
and Starling models.
NousResearch is a kind of--
they started as just a guy.
Teknium was fine-tuning
models and now is a company
for fine-tuning models.
OpenBMB in China has been doing
a lot of preference data sets.
They recently released some
data sets called UltraInteract,
which is some math
preference data for doing
RLHF and fine-tuning.
Argilla is a startup around
building tools to annotate data,
is focused on preference data.
And there's even
just individuals
that are driving this
narrative, so Maxime and Jon.
There's just a lot of people.
Model merging is something
I didn't talk about,
but it's like TPO but
taking it even farther,
where it's-- model
merging is so accessible.
You don't need a
GPU to merge models.
It's a for loop.
So people are going
to try it and there's
going to be iteration on it.
So in this alignment
space, never
bet against people where
they can just try things
and see what's better,
and then eventually learn.
That's what model
merging is, and it's
going to be here to stay.
So thanks for listening.
I'm happy to take questions.
And thanks to my many teammates
at Hugging Face and AI2
that made it look like I
did so many of these things.
But there's a lot of great
contributors that underlie this.
So I'll slow down and drink some
water and answer some questions,
but thanks for coming again.
Yeah, so the top
question on scores--
please rate them
because it's easy for me
to see them-- was about odds
ratio preference alignment.
I think being agnostic to
the method is the best thing,
but you probably need to
be good at engineering
to get really good at one method
to get a specific model out.
And getting these deliverables
important to getting
recognition.
I don't know if people can
talk via microphone, which is
a much more natural experience.
But I'm just going to
keep talking to myself.
[CHUCKLES]
There's a question around
the future of alignment,
given simple methods can
circumvent fine tuning.
I think that the
future of alignment
is like, safety is not the
only thing that matters.
There's a lot of promise
showing that alignment helps
with how much people
like the model,
so how much RLHF improves
the user experience
and how much it improves
code and math abilities.
So like while
everyone hates Q-Star,
Q-Star has some things
to guide towards,
which are using synthetic
data in RL search and stuff
to improve the raw
capabilities, rather than
just talking about safety.
OK, onwards.
Yeah, people are asking about
the fact that Llama 3 uses--
Llama 3 said that they use
instruction fine-tuning,
rejection sampling, DPO, and PPO
for their aligned models, which
I was like, I don't
know how they're
using all of these things.
But I think they're shifting
the abilities incrementally
to provide nice initialization
for the next method
and to keep being able
to use new human data
and make the metrics go up.
I think over time, that
will become simpler.
In the future, Meta will not
have this convoluted five stage
multimethod process.
And we'll figure out a way to
distill that to one algorithm.
Pitfalls of synthetic data
is repetitiveness and not
robust distributions.
So most of the synthetic data
sets out there are about--
they have very similar things
in there, and that is--
like, the models are going
to generalize less well
and probably get less boosts
from alignment training
if there's not this kind
of general improvement
to capabilities.
So we want to take some
in-person questions.
oh, yeah, that's much better.
[CHUCKLING]
Does anyone have some in-person
questions to ask Nathan?
OK.
Hi.
Thank you so much for the talk.
What do you think are the
greatest hotspots of research
or work in terms of
personalized language models,
and where do you see them
having the most impact?
This is one of the things that
I'm excited about, the local LLM
community.
I'm not particularly
ideologically aligned
with the effective
accelerationist stuff,
but I do think that
they have a lot of drive
to create a language model
that they like to use.
So therefore, there's going to
be things we learn from them.
And it's kind of a
classic like, how
to integrate
multiple communities.
So it's like academics
aren't used to looking there,
but I'm sure there's
a lot to learn there.
Yeah.
I guess there are
multiple questions
about advice for the field,
whether it's grad school or--
I'll give my advice with
the caged advice that
is that you should be very wary
of listening to people's advice
because it based
on their situation.
But I think that the
most important thing
you can do in the
field that's crazy
is just keep trying
to develop skills
and keep trying
to build something
that you think matters.
Because it's like, at
the end of the day,
that's where you're
making progress on.
And you'll never be able to
keep track of everything,
and that's OK.
And I can't keep
track of everything,
and I'm still trying to train
models and build data sets.
So it's just like,
grad school is about
learning to do research.
And that still has value.
But industry is also fun if
you want to do a startup.
So there's not
like-- you just have
to think about what
you want to do.
I think someone sent me--
you can hear me, right?
Yeah.
--sent me a question
through Zoom.
A quick question, you indicated
that making lower methods
work with reinforcement
learning is tricky.
Do you think lower methods work
well with DPO or its variance?
I haven't seen it be
particularly successful.
So that's my general
rule of thumb,
is I really wait to
go deep into a method
until there's been a
model release that's
in the relevant ballpark
with that type of--
with that method.
So the fact that it's
been around for so long
and hasn't happened
could be a blind spot.
But I think that there's
some weirdness that's
preventing it from happening.
Great.
OK, another one.
Thank you for the talk.
You mentioned GPT-4 being
used as an evaluation metric,
but it causes data
contamination.
What are some ways
to mitigate this?
Oh, man.
Yeah.
I mean, this is why it's, like,
nice to have human evaluation.
But I don't know if
I have an answer.
At this point, I'm kind of
fried from reading Llama 3 stuff
and giving this lecture.
But that's the
fundamental problem,
is how to disambiguate various
evaluation, various biases
and evaluation and still
get the signal out of them.
Right.
OK, one more.
Give me a second.
Thanks.
For stuff like Llama 3
training on so many tokens,
like 15 trillion,
would that actually
make it harder to
align this model
without losing some capabilities
learned from this overtraining?
It's not technically
overtrained,
but every model will
have a different point
by which they're released.
So it's like, that's why you
need a different learning rate
and batch size and
data sets for models.
So you will need a different
way of continuing it.
But that is a common
confusion on how--
like, I mean, I don't even
have an intuition for it,
just to know that I have
bought this thing in the past
and been proven wrong about it.
But it's like, it's not that
it's overtrained or harder
to fine-tune.
It's just that there's more
information into the model.
And as you continue to do this,
the model can keep learning.
It just takes more and more data
to get marginal improvements.
So Meta is willing to invest
more money into the model
to make it just a bit better,
but that should only help.
It shouldn't hurt.
All right, great.
Here's another one.
Do you think synthetic data
generation, like Cosmopedia,
is the way to go for making
controlled or trusted
domain-specific models?
I think it would be very good.
I also think it's a good
way to get around the fact
that Google is paying
rent at $60 million a year
to use their data so that we can
no longer train on the newest
Reddit data.
I think that Cosmopedia
and synthetic data
sets at a large scale
can be a way around this.
And there are
rumors that industry
is doing something similar.
Give me a second.
I think there's
one that I missed.
Could you please
share some insights
on why you are finding
PPO better than DPO?
It's mostly like it ends up
extracting more from the data.
So it's like the
benchmarks end up
being a little bit better if
we get it set up correctly
with the same starting point.
So it's like, you choose
a set of evaluations
that you care about.
And you look at them.
And through
fine-tuning the-- it's
primarily a group of great
grad students doing this.
It's just running a ton
of models and trainings,
and they're seeing
that PPO reliably can
be doing a little bit better.
And it's like, this is the
fine margins that a lot of AI
works on nowadays.
Great.
Do you foresee a better
evaluation method
to be determined by a stronger
or more specialized model, which
means rule-based metrics
are dead forever?
[INAUDIBLE],, I try not
to say no to things.
This is becoming
philosophical, which
is like, I'm trying not to say
no to things in the language
model space with how fast
things are progressing.
It's like, I should try not to
bet against progress continuing.
This goes for pretraining
and alignment.
And it's like, at multiple
stages in the last few months
come to benefit me.
So it's like, if you just assume
that things will get better
and they will work,
it's like, just
makes it a little bit easier to
wrap your head around things.
One last one here from--
give me a sec.
At its core, an LLM is
trying to approximate
a complex distribution.
Would you say that alignment
is the process of squashing
specific parts of
this distribution
according to what humans prefer?
Yeah, I think that's
phrased generally enough
that I could get behind it.
It is.
It's like, alignment is about
changing the distribution,
and it can be multiple tokens.
It's like a
multiterm prediction.
RL is not just autoregressive.
It can be these multistring
different things that
are getting shifted around, and
it's a really different loss
function.
Here's one from--
how do you envision
the usage of watermark for
both open and closed language
[AUDIO OUT]
I think it, a lot of times,
feels like a losing battle.
I think that a practical
solution in the future
is that a lot of-- if you want
to prove something that is human
made, you can prove that
it was generated by a human
by having a certain
tool, rather than trying
to understand if a specific
content was made by an AI.
So the assumption will be that
all content was made by an AI
unless proven to be human.
It's not what I would consider
a sociologically good answer.
It just seems like
a practical one.
Makes sense.
I think we have a
few more minutes.
So if anybody has any
last minute questions,
feel free to send them over
to me on the Zoom chat.
Yeah, this is-- that was much
better than me half-reading
the question.
[CHUCKLING]
All right, here's one.
What are your thoughts on
different optimization functions
to train large language
models rather than using MLE?
What could be good
research directions there?
I think this is the whole
idea of what RLHF represents.
And that's why,
if you ask people
who have been in NLP longer, one
of the most compelling arguments
for me is like you now have
extreme flexibility on the loss
function, while we were
kind of limited on what
our regressive losses could do.
So there's arguments that
it's like, why is there
any limit if we could just keep
doing more and more tokens of RL
training?
It's a really general
framing, but RL's loss
function-- you make it so that
the training of a language model
can incorporate many
different things.
And that's very exciting.
That could be like the
10 year goal of RLHF.
To what extent is training
on adversarial data
effective for defending
against crescendo
and other simple
multi-turn attacks.
I haven't spent as much time
on safety as I would want to,
but I think it's like--
it'll be this everlasting dance
where, if you have example data,
you can defend against it.
But it will not be impossible
to generate new data.
So mostly, it comes
down to the use case
that you're looking
at protecting.
So if you want to protect
something really important,
you need to have
layers on that are not
just sensitive to a new
prompting technique,
but limit what the model can do.
It's like a use-focused theme.
Well, the kind of whole--
security is a very
complicated thing, otherwise.
Here's one on quantization.
Do you see potential
in quantization methods
such as BitNet, like 1.58 bit?
If so, do you think BitNet
will become popular?
I have no idea.
I wouldn't-- this
is what I mean.
It's like, OK, sounds cool.
Wouldn't rule it out.
You think there
is a need or a way
to control large-scale data
extraction from large language
models like Cosmopedia?
I do think there's
a lot of wills
in a lot of ways
to explore making
the synthetic data better.
I think it's very early.
I have a project
that's going on it,
and it is one of the few
ways that can generate
more tokens, which is like--
people are actually
running out of tokens,
especially if you try not to
train on things that you're not
supposed to train on.
It's like, then you can
just generate more data.
And as we've seen with Llama,
if you have the compute,
more data will help you.
Let's see, self-play-like
make things.
Any chance you can expand
upon or share your opinions
on self-play-like
things, like OpenAI
Superalignment [? work. ?]
I think people will keep
using language models
in the loop of training
other language models,
but it's a broad field
that doesn't have
full agreement on how to do it.
OK, great.
And I think we're
pretty much out of time.
So if folks want to get in
touch or have more questions,
can they email you or--
Yeah.
OK, great.
But yeah, thanks so much
again for taking the time
and giving us such a great talk.
So yeah, give it up for Nathan.
Thanks, everyone.
And I think the slides, as well
as the Hugging Face collection,
are all posted on our
website, as well as Discord
so in case anybody
wants to follow along.
Sounds good.
Thanks a lot for having me.
Yeah, no worries.
See around [? Stan. ?] Bye-bye.